<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvonderful prognostication or prediction for these seuen yeeres insuing shewing the strange and wonderfull comets and meatuors, beginning this present yeere, 1604 / written in French by the Lord of Billy ...</title>
            <author>Billy, Himbert de, ca. 1544-ca. 1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 414.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S14</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21467047</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 21467047</idno>
            <idno type="VID">24001</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17295)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 24001)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1738:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvonderful prognostication or prediction for these seuen yeeres insuing shewing the strange and wonderfull comets and meatuors, beginning this present yeere, 1604 / written in French by the Lord of Billy ...</title>
                  <author>Billy, Himbert de, ca. 1544-ca. 1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For W. Ferbrand, and are to be s[ol]d in Popes-head Ally, neare t[h]e Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Lon[do]n :</pubPlace>
                  <date>16[0]4.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁸.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ephemerides.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:24001:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24001:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> VVONDERFVLL PROGNOSTICATION: OR, PREDICTION, for theſe ſeuen yeeres inſuing: Shewing the ſtrange and <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull Comets and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuors:</hi> beginning this preſent yeere. 1604.</p>
            <p>Written in French by the Lord of <hi>Billy,</hi> Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie to the moſt illuſtrious Princeſſe, the Lady <hi>Celeſtine Olal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pa,</hi> Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe of <hi>Pancoſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative engraving</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>W. Ferbrand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and are to be ſold in Popes-head Ally<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neare the Exchange, 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1603" type="prognostication">
               <pb facs="tcp:24001:2"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:24001:2"/>
               <head>A Prediction vpon this preſent yeere. 1603.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the Configuration of the Heauens in this yeeres Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolution, and the Sunnes entraunce (the fountaine of heate &amp; light) into the ſigne of <hi>Aries,</hi> we may ſpeake of the principal matter therby ſignified: and this Reuolution of the Worlde hath almoſt the ſelfe ſame ſignification as that in the yeere. 1602. For <hi>Mars</hi> ioyned to the Sunne, ſhall force himſelfe with all his power to oppreſſe the Mortals with greeuous Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and other diſeaſes, whereby (if God pittie vs not) many thouſandes of men ſhall periſh by Peſtilence, Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine, and by the Sword: as alſo the Moone infortunated by <hi>Mars</hi> by a fourth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, ſhewes the ſame: For there ſhall happen great controuerſies among Souldiers, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny robberies ſhall be done: alſo, diuers Citties
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:24001:3"/> ſhall be tormented and vexed with diuers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils &amp; troubles, by reaſon of the furie of Warre. In briefe, by reaſon that <hi>Mars</hi> will force him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to vexe men more and more, many tumults ſhall be heald, great exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ditiens in Warre ſhall happen, and many ſhall be ſurpriſed with feare. He that can keepe himſelfe at home, let him not trau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, becauſe that moſt like thereby he may haue ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>hap: many complaintes of griefe and ſodaine loſſes ſhall be heard: he that ſhall ariue at home, ſhall bring but little goodneſſe with him. The fourth aſpect of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aturne</hi> and <hi>Venus.</hi> foreſheweth great vexations and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences to ariſe amongſt Women, by reaſon of adulteries and fornications. Now meetinges and aſſemblies ſhal be ſummoned in diuers Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, to appeaſe the differences of this time, but nothing ſhall be concluded: and therefore with <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lomon</hi> I will ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Eccles.</hi> 9. <hi>I returned and ſaw vnder the Sunne, that the ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e is not to the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t, nor batta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le to the ſtrong, nor yet bread to the wiſe, nor alſo riches vnto men of vnderſtanding, neither yet ſauour to men of knowledge, but time and chaunce commeth to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This yeere the Moone ſhall be twice Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: to wit, the .xiiii. of May, and at .xi. of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:24001:3"/> clocke and .xxx. minutes after noone, and ſhall be Eclipſed .viii. poyntes and .lv. min. ſhe ſhall continue .iii. houres and .v minuts, and will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare blacke in colour, mixed with palenes. The other ſhall be the .viii. of Nouember, at .vi. of the clocke and .xxii. min. after noone, in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe .iii. de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rees and .xxxviii. min her continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ſhall be two houres and viii. min. And in colour ſhall appeare as the former: and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, Aſh-colour mixed with White: which Eclipſes are not without great ſignification, no more then are the Coniunctions of the higheſt Planets. <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Iupiter,</hi> with the others in the firſt face of <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> the higheſt lodge of <hi>Saturne,</hi> and mansion of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> which will be celebrated the .x of December.</p>
               <p>Touching the effectes of the Eclipſe on the xiiii. of May, appearing in the .x. and .xi. houſes of the heauen, proclaymes death vnto Kinges, Princes and Eccleſiaſticall perſons, eſpecially in their manly age: and by reaſon that ſhe hath her operation in the fierie triplicitie, ſhe ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth death of Cattell, the exile of a great King or Prince, immpriſonmentes or death, hate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Commons and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> greater ſort, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall hates and differences <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>tions of great Hoaſtes and horrible War<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>anſl-aughters,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:24001:4"/> fire, theeuery, rapines, and depopulations: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely birthes, Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, Peſtilences, hot infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, death and barrenneſſe of fruites, and nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mutations, eſpecially in the Regions which are ſubiect to the ſignes of this Eclipſe. And by reaſon that ſhe is found in the firſt tenth of the ſigne, ſhe ſignifies theftes and robberies. And for the ſaid great Coniunction, there is no doubt but they are of great ſignification, as being the firſt which happeneth vnder this fierie triangle. For ſince the time of <hi>Charlemaine,</hi> which are 800 yeeres agoe, they haue not been ſeene in this manner.</p>
               <p>As likewiſe in the .xiii. yeere of our Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhe was in the ſame face of <hi>Sagittarius:</hi> and from that time vntill the time of <hi>Charlemaine,</hi> which was <hi>Anno. 809.</hi> After which, followed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers Eclipſes, apparitions of Comets, as after this alſo will enſue ſome greeuous accidentes: from which, God defend vs. For there will hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen alterations as well in Houſholdes as in Eſtates, Common-wealthes, as Religion: for theſe great Coniunctions in the fiery ſignes, do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raw vp exhalations, which inflaming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Region of the ayre, cauſe this Comet or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Starre, which although by reaſon of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>ſtaunce of the earth, ſhee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:24001:4"/> ſeemes litle vnto our ſight, yet is ſhe of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame and incredible greatneſſe. And as after the ſame Coniunctions in the time of <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,</hi> the death of ſome great Men or great Lightes of the world did enſue: ſo muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe be aſſured, that the death of great perſons will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this (which God defend:) Alſo, thereby is foreſhewed great motiues to Warre, and great alteration of Lawes, Sectes, and Religion, as well in the Politicke as Spirituall Eſtates. For this fiery Triangle hath his proper ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation vpon Monarkes and great Religions. As we ſee that the Chriſtian fayth began vnder this Triangle, and likewiſe was greatly aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented vnder the ſame, in the time of <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,</hi> as well in number of perſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as in Pompes and Ceremonies: As for the other Triangles and great Coniunctions contayned vnder them, their ſignifications are vpon the ſectes and deuiſions in the great Religion, as are the ſectes of the foure begging Orders, and others more rich in gyftes: theſe foure begging Orders began. 400. yeeres ſince, in which time began the greateſt Coniunctions in the ayrie Triangle, which is the ſignes of <hi>Gemini, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra,</hi> and <hi>Aquarius,</hi> and continued. 200. yeeres. At that time, there liued a great Aſtronomer, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:24001:5"/> 
                  <hi>Guido Bonatus,</hi> who ſayth thus of theſe Sectes. <q>
                     <hi>Sicut finis quando incips ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cta ſine religio Auguſtini, &amp; ſecta Benedicti, &amp; ſecta fraetrum mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum quae incipit. Era Ara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um 609 Anno menſe Rabe viti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, Era Chriſti 1211. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>us princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>m fuit tale aſcendens quod ipſa ſupra decabit om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es alias ſectas, &amp; ordines ſub. Romana Eccleſia de gentes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſed cius ſinem dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re non a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, timore ne inci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am in remorem v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lga. Eri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> tamen public<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s valde cum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>nerit as de ipſo rumor menſus.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1604" type="prognostication">
               <head>The Prediction vpon the yeere. 1604.</head>
               <p>BY this yeeres Reuolution which is the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traunce of the Sunne into the ſigne of <hi>Aries.</hi> we are ſhewed, that in many things ſhe agreeth with the former yeeres, and all thinges ſhall happen in ſelfe ſame maner as we haue foretolde. For ſhe ſignifies calamities and troubles in Religion, and in the eſtates of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions perſons. Item, diſcontentions in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of great men, as the laſt Coniunction of <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> in the fiery ſigne doe ſhew, which threaten de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iptes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ages. She is furthermore ſeene to threaten hates and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:24001:5"/> deſcentions betweene Kinges &amp; Princes, which ſhall cauſe Warres and dangerous alterations. This Coniunction (becauſe ſhe is changed from the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry to the fiery Triplicity, according to the <hi>Arabian</hi> decrees) is mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> euill, and ſignifieth great miſchiefes vnto mankind. <hi>Peter Ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o</hi> Card<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nall of <hi>Camerace,</hi> ſayth, that <hi>Gallia</hi> or <hi>Fraunce,</hi> is vnder the domination of <hi>Iupiter:</hi> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erefore by this Conſtellation ſhe is ſubi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te vnto diuers diſcommodities, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efes, &amp; loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as him ſelfe witneſſeth to haue been found by ſundry obſeruations. Wherefore I beſeech Almighty God to make that Prognoſticator a lya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and to keepe her from all hurt and danger. Moreouer, the applycation of <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> to the body of <hi>Saturne</hi> ſeemes to foretell the death of ſome noble Lady: and alſo moyſt and hot Sickneſſes, Collickes, Paſſions, Head-aches, and the Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan diſeaſe vnto the common people, and many Kinges and Princes ſhall ſcarce be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to be ſeene, ſo much they ſhall feare the fury, anger, and ſedicious of the Commons. This yeere in our Horizon ſhall be no Eclipſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1605" type="prognostication">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:24001:6"/>
               <head>Predictions vpon the yeere 1605.</head>
               <p>BY the Celeſtiall Figure of this yeeres Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolution, which is the Sunnes entraunce into the Celeſtiall weather, <hi>Saturne</hi> is in the. 12. houſe, who by his myſchieuous beames doth infortunate the Sunne: to wit, by a fourth aſpect. Item, the Moone is found to be conioyne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to <hi>Mars</hi> in the third houſe of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: which lightes being infortunated, ſeeme to foretell many euils, and diſcommodities to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in the world: wherefore with <hi>Leouice</hi> I will ſay, I cannot tell how it happeneth, that ſo many great Eclipſes (eſpecially of the Sunne) do fall in ſo few yeeres, whereby greeuous and moſt wretched accidentes are preſaged. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps theſe be the latter dayes, when as all piety and charity ſhall waxe cold, trueth &amp; iuſtice ſhall be oppreſſed: and all thinges elſe ſhall be mixed, diſturbed, and turned vpſide downe, and the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part ſet behinde by torments and ſeditions: and finally nothing elſe ſhall be expected, but ſpoyle and ruine of the common ſociety: wherefore with pure and rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ant hartes we ought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the Almighty God: and with vnceſſant
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:24001:6"/> humble prayers implore his Maieſtie, to diuert his furie from vs, and that he depriue vs not of the deuine lyght of his holy Goſpell (wherein our eternall ſaluation doth conſiſt) nor permit the ſame to be rent &amp; extinguiſhed by the wicked.</p>
               <p>This yeere the Moone ſhall be twice Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the Sunne once.</p>
               <p>The firſt Eclipſe of the Moone ſhall be on the 23. day of March, at. 7 of the clocke. 35. minuts after noone, at the Dragons head, and ſhall be obſcured. 11. poynts and 40. min. and ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue (from the beginning to the ende) 3. houres 24. min. She ſhall appeare of colour blacke, mixed with greene and red: and by reaſon that ſhe happeneth in an ayrie and humane ſigne, ſhe ſignifies famine and greeuous ſickneſſes and peſtilences, tempeſtious and hurtfull windes: Her effectes ſhall continue three monethes and eight dayes.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Eclipſe of the Moone ſhall be the 17. day of September at 3 of the clocke and 14. minuts, in colour blacke, mixed with pale and aſhe colour: and becauſe ſhe comes in the fourth houſe, ſhe ſignifies change of Lawes, Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Sectes: and moreouer, becauſe ſhe is in a fiery ſigne, ſhe ſignifies the ſelfe ſame things which are mentioned in the yeere. 1603. the. 14.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:24001:7"/> day of May: and her being in <hi>Aries.</hi> ſignifies a corruption to light vpon the Fruites, on Vines and Figtrees.</p>
               <p>The Sunne likewiſe ſhall be Eclipſed on the ſecond of October, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2. of the clocke and 5 min. after noone, and ſhall be obſcured. 11. poyntes and 38. min<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the firſt beginning ſhal be neare 48. min. after noone, the middle at 2. of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> clocke and 5. min. and the end ſhal be at. 3. and. 22. min: ſo that from the beginning vntill the end, ſhal be two houres and 34. min<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which (as <hi>Procl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciu<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ſayth) w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th the Sunne paſſing vnder the eight ſtation of the Heauen, vnder the ſigne of <hi>Libra,</hi> is accuſtomed to foreſhew the death of ſome great King or Prince, ſedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> warres, famine, and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtilence: w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ala</hi> ſaith, When as the Sunne is Eclipſed, it can not be, (vnleſſe God appoynt otherwiſe) but ſome great accident is to be expected in the world, according to the quantity of the Eclipſe. And <hi>Virgil</hi> ſaith, When as the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> giues a ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, who dares ſay that he foreſheweth any falſe thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and fore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the tum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lts of the blind w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rres, &amp; ſecret fraudes are at hand. The S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> alſo pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yed <hi>Rome</hi> when as <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>rs</hi> death he co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered his face with a blacke and obſcure vayle: and then the great wicked<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of the world made
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:24001:7"/> them to feare an euerlaſting darkneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ouice</hi> ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, O King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Princes which are borne vnder the ſignes of the Ballance and the Ramme: alſo the Prouinces &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es which a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſubiect vnto the firſt quadrangle of the Zod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke, and to the ſigne of <hi>Scorpio,</hi> Many greeuous euils are foreſeene to fall vpon you, extreame mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s are euen at hand. I could (as he ſayth) haue extended the Reuolutions at the world vntill the next two yeeres, vntill which, the effectes of this Eclipſe ſhall continue: But <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lato</hi> commaunds me here to hold my peace, for ſo he writeth. It is moſt manifeſt, that of lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time there hath not been ſeene any great thing, nor the like ſhall not be ſeene in long time after<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Darkneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen at high mid-day. The effectes ſhall begin on the 11. day of Aprill 1606. and ſhal c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſe on the 10. day of October. 1608. He ſhall appeare of a moſt deformed colour, gray, ſea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> colour, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and becauſe ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mes in the ſigne of the ayrie and humane triangle, it ſignifies greeuous ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, diſeaſes, and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, with tempeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and moſt pernitions windes: and being in the ſecond fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of <hi>Libr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Proclus</hi> ſayth, that ſhe ſignifies death of Spirituall men, eſpecially in their middle age: but the kind <hi>Venus,</hi> that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of the places of the Eclipſe, may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:24001:8"/> moderate theſe Celeſtiall Menaces, as a ſecond cauſe: for vnto their firſt cauſe, who is the cauſe of cauſes, moderatour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f all thinges, the honour and prayſe of all muſt be referred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1606" type="prognostication">
               <head>The Prediction vpon the yeere. 1606.</head>
               <p>BY this yeeres Reuolution, which is the Sunnes entraunce into the ſigne of the Martiall Ramme, the ouerthrow or ſpoyle of ſome Region or Citie is ſignified vnto vs, ſhewing many other diſcommodities to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the world: of which we haue made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Eclipſe of the Sunne: But <hi>Mars</hi> poſſeſſing the ſeuenth Celeſtiall houſe, which is in the. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> aſpect of <hi>Mercury:</hi> and <hi>Saturne</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the fourth aſpect of the Sunne, which holdes the eight Celeſtiall ſtation: theſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhew the deathes of many men: ſubtiltie &amp; craft ſhall encreaſe: yet he that ſhall haue digged the pit, and pitched the ſnare, ſhall fall into it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Moreouer, there will be litle or no conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation vpon Captiues, or others put in captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, becauſe there will be multitudes of Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the greater part ſhall lyue by hope, which notwithſtanding ſhall obtaine nothing: and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:24001:8"/> men of Warre ſhall be caſheer'd. Likewiſe there ſhall be great Warres, and many hidden inuentions betweene diuers Lordes in diuers Prouinces, in ſuch ſort, that it ſhall be hard to diſcerne whom amongſt friendes ſhall be true and faythfull. <hi>Mercury</hi> will cauſe many deceipt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Counſayles, wherefore it is to be feared, leaſt many do endure euill Cataſtrophes, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and conuerſions. What reſtes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes this Profeſſion, we leaue it to be diſputed of the learned, and louers of this Art, ſince with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t danger the myſteries thereof cannot be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted. This ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re in our Horiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, ſhall be ſeene no Eclipſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1607" type="prognostication">
               <head>The Prediction of the yeere. 1607.</head>
               <p>THere ſhall be one Ecipſe of the Moone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he 28. of Auguſt, at two a clocke and halfe an houre after midnight, and ſhall be dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned in 4, poyntes 28. min. in the 13. degree of the ſigne <hi>Piſces,</hi> which ſignifieth death to watry Creatures, principally to Fiſhes. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Fountaynes and Riuers: and this Eclipſe is made in the ſecond 10. of <hi>Piſces,</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending and hurting Sowing vniuerſally: a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:24001:9"/> becauſe it is made in the houſe of Religion, it ſignifieth l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe to Eccleſiaſticall perſons and for that it is made in the watry Triplicitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth death of ignoble perſons, long ſeditions Warres, and doma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to watry things, and ſuch as li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in the Seas: notwithſtanding, <hi>Iupiter</hi> Lord of the Eclipſe, the friend of Nature, ſayes better things, that is, increaſe of all things, but peculia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, lyberally giueth to men glory, health of body<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> reſt of ſpirit, ioy, peace, great helpe of wealth, reconciliation with great men, augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Religion in Kinges &amp; Princes, principally thoſe which he Iouials, good renowne mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>itie, liberalitie, and good deedes to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: aboundance of Annimals, profi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able for the vſe of men: and will kill thinges in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ble, aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting the Fruites of the earth preſeruing eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially Corne and Grai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and ſuch thinges, making the bleſſing &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nigni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of the heauens in full force: the Ayre temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and healthfull, breathing moyſt bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es, holſome and my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kie ſhewers on terreſtrtall things: the Waters to haue moderate Floodes, tempering the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wing and eb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ings of the Sea, gentle calmes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which will make Nauigations proſperous and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table garding from Pyrats, and temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eous ſtormes: and to conclude, and is Author of all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:24001:9"/> happyneſſe. Behold what the good <hi>Iupiter</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth, being dominator of this gear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly correcteth the malice of the euill. The great God ſo graunt it, to his euerlaſting glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1608" type="prognostication">
               <head>Predictions in generall for the yeere. 1608.</head>
               <p>THe. 19. day of March at two a clocke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 29. min. after noone, this yeere ſhal reuine, the former Reuolution being accomply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and the Sunne great conductor of Knightes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrant, paſſing through the wandring troupe, will make his entry in the houſe of <hi>Mars,</hi> taking for enſigne the Celeſtiall weather, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with vs ſhall riſe vpon our Hemiſpheere the 25. degree of the Lion, with the head of the Dragon Lunaried, <hi>Saturne</hi> with <hi>Capricorne</hi> in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Houſe, and <hi>Mars</hi> in the ſame ſigne, his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halation. <hi>Iupiter</hi> in the ſigne of <hi>Aries, Mercury</hi> in <hi>Piſces,</hi> and the Moone in the height of heauen into <hi>Taurus</hi> her exaltation, there ſhe ſhall finde her ſelfe the beſt lodged and more diguiſied then all the others: and for that ſhe hath participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the dominion with <hi>Saturne,</hi> after her the moſt worthy, the which being lodged in the houſe of Infirmities with Venus in the water<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:24001:10"/> powrer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> doth foreſhew ſome peculiar, Sickneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, if the benignitie of <hi>Venus</hi> (and God aboue all) breake not her malice. Item, the Winter following to be cold, rigorous, ſnowy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſie, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yly, euill and peſtilent: alſo thicke and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely cloudy: cloudes full of tempeſtes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rawneſſe, windes, Innundations of Currents and Floodes, flowinges and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings: in the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere Seas hard and perilous Nauigations. Shypwrackes, and many times Earth-quakes, corruption, ſcarcity, and death to Fiſh, &amp; deadly euils to wild beaſtes: Domage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and harmefull to fruites, pothearbes, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to thoſe which belong to the vſe of man, by reaſon of Wormes, Caterpillers, and Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtes, which ſhall eate them to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h their hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: But theſe euils are more vpon beaſtes, then vpon men, becauſe ſhe is in <hi>Capricorne,</hi> halfe Goate &amp; haſte Fiſh. All which things, the good &amp; Almighty great God can change, if it pleaſe him, and make as nothing, proouing vs vayne lyers, euen vnſpeakable vayne. The fortunate part of this Reuolution is in ſufficient good place, and promiſeth vs (being rad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ated and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned by <hi>Iupiter)</hi> to be a good portion of the yeere, and to goe well with Marchants. But the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ner Figur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Heauen, being ioyned wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:24001:10"/> 
                  <hi>Saturne</hi> the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euolent enemy of Nature, in the ſigne of <hi>Capricorne,</hi> ſhall make the ſame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo bountifull, for as much as <hi>Saturne</hi> denoteth intemperance of too much moyſture and cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, more then is cuſtomable.</p>
               <p>The firſt of Auguſt at three a clocke 29. min. after noone, there ſhall be an Eclipſe, or rather the Sunnes labour by the Moones interpoſition betwixt him &amp; our ſight, who ſhall couer him 3. poyntes 44. min. One may behold this his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerture in water (hee ſhyning) and by a ſaffron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like yellowneſſe in the cloudes, againſt a wall, and againſt the earth, and ſhould be obſerued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſayd houre, and ſomething after, that one may ſee him couer'd by the Moone, as well in the beginnyng as in the ende. The ſayd Eclipſe ſhall be made in the. 17. degree of the ſigne of <hi>Leo,</hi> the houſe of the Sunne, and in the. 8. ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the heauens, which is of death, we rayſing vpon our Horizon the 15 degree of <hi>Sagittarius:</hi> and amonſt other things, it betokeneth the death of ſome great Perſonage: from which God keepe him (if he pleaſe) and vs from the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges and euill effectes of this Eclipſe. In the ſecond face of <hi>Leo,</hi> ſhe threatneth with troubles and detriment, the great and powerfull. <hi>Venus</hi> Lady of the South Angle, following the place
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:24001:11"/> of the Eclipſe, hath her part with the Sunne in domination of the ſame: and therefore the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes ſhall not be ſo euill as ſome are.</p>
               <p>The Countryes and Cities ſubiect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the firſt Quadrangle of the Zodiaque, and thoſe perſons which in the Horoſcope of their Natiuitie, or in their Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olution ſhall haue the place of the Eclipſe oppoſite from them, and the Planets, ſhall taſte more bitterly ſuch effectes (if any are) then others. From all which, the good &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God keepe vs, if it pleaſe him. Yet further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, vpon the firſt day of May, the two euill Planets Saturne and <hi>Mars,</hi> ſhall be togeather, conioyned in the firſt poynt of the ſigne of <hi>Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> the houſe of the ſorrowfull <hi>Saturne,</hi> which neither promiſeth to vs goodneſſe, nor to Dame Flora and her lytle ones, by their intemperate heate and frozen hayle, thunder, and rayne: of them it is ſayd, <q>
                     <hi>Cum malus malo, ſungitur angetur omne malum.</hi>
                  </q> Prayers and ſupplications ſhould therefore then be made to the modera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our of all thinges for the conſeruation of them. The aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Pagans</hi> celebrated in that time, the <hi>Robi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals</hi> &amp; <hi>Florals:</hi> one was by the decree of Sibilla, the other by the decree of <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ma Pompilius;</hi> and in place of the ſayd prayers, they yet celebate dayly Rogations, &amp; the Proceſſion of <hi>S. Marke.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1609" type="prognostication">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:24001:11"/>
               <head>Predictions for the yeere. 1609.</head>
               <p>THe tenth of the month of March at. 8. of the clocke. 24. minutes. 55. ſecondes after noone, the former Reuolution is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, and the only e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of this world wil make his entry vpon the ſigne of the <hi>Ramme, Mars</hi> with vs then riſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the 25. degree of the <hi>Balance,</hi> the Sunne &amp; Moone oppoſite th'one to the other in the ſame ſigne of the <hi>Balance,</hi> the Moone in her full, the Lady <hi>Venus</hi> in her <hi>Bull</hi> iayned with <hi>Iupiter;</hi> the gentle Lady of this Aſcend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, and of this yeere, being lodged in an angle of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccident: and becauſe ſhe is ioyned with <hi>Iupiter,</hi> the friende of Nature, and herſelfe alſo is fortunate, denoteth her influence of this Reuolution as we haue ſayd of <hi>Iupiter</hi> in the yeere precedent: Beſides, peculiarly ſhe ſhall giue to men (I meane as a ſecond cauſe) health of body, beautie, tranquilitie and reſt of minde, a happie yeere increaſe of goodes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect &amp; honour, good eſteeme amongſt the better ſort, principally <hi>ven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rions</hi> and Muſitions, ſhall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:24001:12"/> haue of the beſt and ſhall be more enclyned to ſportes, dauncings, reuellinges, banq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tinges, voluptuouſneſſe, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>age: then they were vſually inclyned. Beſides <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll cauſe ſweete, moyſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſhewers, at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing earth the bleſſings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Nature. She ſhall cauſe freſh gentle Winds tempered of heauen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ayre, cleereneſſe and happy paſſage for S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> filling the Floodes and Foun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ames, and the Trees with Fruites. Briefly, ſhe pron <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th ayre better then the former, although <hi>Saturne</hi> in his <hi>Aquarius</hi> would haue it as the precedent. But if Iupiter once take him, he will thruſt him from his raigne: yet during the Winter, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> marching by <hi>Capricorne,</hi> and the water filler his houſes, ſhall make it mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>old then it cuſtomably is. For Eclipſes, we ſhall haue this yeere two of the Moone.</p>
               <p>The firſt ſhall he the. 10. day of Ianuary at two a clocke after midnight, and ſhall be darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to. 8. poyntes and. 18. minutes, and ſhall endure about ſome three houres: it ſhall be made in. 29. degree, 50. min. of the ſigne of <hi>Cancer,</hi> to the head of the Dragon <hi>Lunaried,</hi> then ſhall well rayſe the. 14. degree of Scorpius, and ſhall be made in the. 10. ſtation of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, the houſe royall, and ſhall continue in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:24001:12"/> ninth, which is of Religion. The good <hi>Iupiter</hi> bearing the prize amongſt the number of the workes towardes the end of the Eclipſe, neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe before the end of the Eclipſe, the Moone ſhall enter in the ſigne of <hi>Leo. Proclus</hi> ſayth, that the Eclipſe being in the laſt tenth degree of <hi>Cancer,</hi> betokeneth to all Armenia &amp; <hi>Affricke,</hi> and other Regions ſubiect to <hi>Cancer,</hi> ſickneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſeditions, and other euils: and for that ſhee paſſeth alſo into the Lyon. ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e denoteth alſo the death of ſome ſoueraigne Prince, and ſcarſity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f all kinde of Grayne. He ſayth alſo, that by the laſt 10. of <hi>Cancer.</hi> ſhee menaſeth the Feminine ſexe with ſickneſſe, ſodayne ſickneſſe of ſome great Prince, or the death of ſome excellent man: and by making her Eclipſe firſt in the Palace royall and of dignity, ſhe denotech ſome diſaſter fortune in the dignity of the great: which God can preſerue if it pleaſe him. And her continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the houſe of Religion, denoteth alſo ſome trouble or euill, principally ſome euill, diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Eccleſiaſticall eſtate. From all which euils, the great GOD delyuer vs, if it pleaſe him.</p>
               <p>There ſhall be an other Eclipſe the. 6 day of Iuly, at. 11. of the clocke. 17 min. after noone, and ſhall be darkoned to. 15. poyntes. 53. min.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:24001:13"/> and ſhall dure 3. houres: it ſhall be made in the 24. degree of the ſigne of <hi>Capricorne,</hi> the houſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the maleuolent <hi>Saturne.</hi> Then ſhall we rayſe in our Horizon the. 5. degree of <hi>Taurus:</hi> now there is no doubt but the euill <hi>Saturne</hi> will beare a ſhare in the domination, beeing that it is made in his houſe, and therefore betokens ſmall good, but rather the euill which we haue before ſpoken of him, in the Reuolution of the yeere 1608. from which, God of his go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>neſſe keepe vs, if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he his good pleaſure. <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lus</hi> ſayth, that the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lipſe being made in the laſt tenth of <hi>Capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corne,</hi> ſignifieth death, and ſedition of ſome great Prince, and tumultuous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſurrections: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made in the eleuenth heau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nly Temple, and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the houſe of worthyneſſe, ſhe deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ill fortune to theſe two Countryes in their ſignifications, to wit, that many ſhall be decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of whom they truſt, and by their friendes: and that many ſhall fall from their dignities. The Countrey and Towne ſubiect to <hi>Capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corne,</hi> and to the firſt Quadrangle of the Zodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dique, and thoſe perſons hauing in the Horoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope of their natiuities, the 24. degr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricorne,</hi> the poynt oppoſite from that of the Sunnes, the Moone and the fiue other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets in that degree of the Eclipſe, and 3. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:24001:13"/> before, and 3. after, ſhall be more ſubiect to the euill effectes of the ſame (if any come) then others. From the which thinges, God of his mercy preſerue vs, if it pleaſe him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1610" type="prognostication">
               <head>Predictions for the yeere 1610.</head>
               <p>THe. 21. day of Marth at two of the clocke 20. minutes 40. ſecondes, the Sunne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductor of the wandring troupe, maketh his entry into the ſigne of the Martiall <hi>Ramme,</hi> with vs there ryſeth vpon our Hemiſphere, the firſt degre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the ſigne of <hi>Capricorne,</hi> the houſe of <hi>Saturne,</hi> the Planet <hi>Mars</hi> in the. 23. degree of the ſame ſigne in the Horoſcope, the moſt dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified of this hand: there being in his exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and there takeing the domination of this yeere: and for that naturally he hath burning, intemperate, and dry effectes, he promiſeth vs no good, but rather by his influence, heate, great drought, and ſcarcitie of rayne, drying vp many Fountaines and Springes of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, corrupting them, and narrowyng the currentes, bringing hotte Windes, peſtilent and horrible exahalations, thunders, lightnings,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:24001:14"/> and by the commixtion of troublous and ſtormy Wyndes, he will cauſe ſubuerſion and loſſe of Shyppes: he will cauſe thoſe Cattell which are moſt neceſſary to the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of man dye, barnyng through pernitious vapours, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>getable thinges ſpringing from the earth, corrupting Fruites ſo as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot in the barnes. He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> denoteth ruines of edifices, embra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> rapes depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulations, cruell ſlaughters of men: Hee will mooue Warres, ciuill ſeditions tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>s of the people, becauſe of the eyranny of the Rule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, through their exactions and cruelties: and by theſe thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es the world ſhall endure contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, baniſhmentes, obſcure and helliſh priſons, and in the ende violent deathes, the vertuous deſpiſed, and the wicked eſteemed, peruertyng thinges vnlawfully: all which euils, the great God through his Almyghty goodneſſe, will turne to nothing, if it pleaſe him, and none ſhall feele theſe calamities, except barbarous and ſtrange Nations, which call not vpon his holy name. <hi>Saturne</hi> marching by the ſigne of Aquarius, in winter ſhall ragingly giue ſnowes and raynes, and great extraordinary froſtes, eſpecially towardes the end.</p>
               <p>Wee ſhall haue two Eclipſes of the Moone this yeere.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:24001:14"/>
               <p>The firſt ſhall be the. 27. of Iune at. 4. of the clocke. 11. min. in the mornyng, in the. 13. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and. 31. min. of the ſigne <hi>Capricorne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> then with vs ſhall ryſe in the ſame. 13. degree of <hi>Cancer,</hi> the Moone touching the poynt of the Occident, in ſuch ſort as we can ſee but the beginnyng thereof: but the people of the Weſt, as the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> and <hi>Low Brittanes</hi> may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſee it then we: ſhee ſhall make it in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Station of the Heauen, and. 6. deg which is of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſeaſes, and therefore ſhe maketh vnfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate theſe two Stations in their ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are of Maryage, and of infirmitie. <hi>Saturne</hi> is Dominator in this Eclipſe, and therefore he threatens vs with euill effectes, as we haue ſayd of him in. 1608 and by his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſecond. 10. of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pricorne,</hi> he ſhall vexe (accordyng to <hi>Proclu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the men of Armes en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eagued agaynſt the Emperour, and hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Captaines and Leaders: fierce aſſaultes of men of warre, incurſions, robberies and capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uities. The Townes and Countrey ſubiect to the ſecond Quadrangle of the Zodiaque, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to <hi>Capricorne,</hi> and the perſons which in their natiuities haue for Aſcendant the degree of the Eclipſe and her oppoſite: and the fiue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Planets ſhall feele moſt ſharpely theſe her
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:24001:15"/> euill effectes (if any come,) but God is aboue all his workes.</p>
               <p>The other Eclipſe of the Moone ſhall be the firſt of December, at three of the clocke. 9. min. in the mornyng, and ſhall be darkoned 5. poynts 42. minutes, and ſhall be made in the 8. degree of the ſigae <hi>Cancer,</hi> ryſing in our Horizon in the. 11. degree of the ſigne <hi>Scorpius,</hi> and ſhall begin in the ſecond ſtation of the Heauen, and ſhall end in the firſt, the beueuolent <hi>Iupiter</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting in <hi>Cancer:</hi> and in him ſhall ioyne to the Eclipſe, preſaging no euill by the Sunne, but rather good, and therefore we will ſpeake lytle of it: onely that we pray to the ſoueraigne worker, creator, and mediator of all thinges, that it will pleaſe him to turne, or moderate all ſiniſters euentes, and Celeſtiall threates, to the end we may ſerue to his glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prognostication">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:24001:15"/>
               <head>A Deſcription of ſuch dayes as are moſt happie and vnhappie, throughout the yeere.</head>
               <p>THeſe dayes hereafter mentioned, were by the Angel reuealed (as ſome ſay) vnto good <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> and others ſay vnto <hi>Iob,</hi> whereby he knew what dayes were good or bad, fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate or vnfortunate, throughout the yeere, to ſell, buy, ſow, plant, and to buylde: to remooue, to vndertake vayages for trade of Merchandize, for Warre, or any other matter: And ſuch dayes being choſen as ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ereafter named, are found to be moſt fortunate: and any thing taken in hand in theſe dayes, can not but haue good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, neither (as our French Author affirmes) ſhall any man haue any loſſe by any bargaine he vndertakes, but ſhall alwayes profite himſelfe. Moreouer, al children which are borne in any of theſe happy dayes, ſhall neuer be poore: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in like ſore either put to Schoole, or to any ſcience, trade, or occupation vpon any of theſe ſayd happie dayes (if he do perſeuer and continue in his eſtate &amp; vocation) ſhall vndoubtedly proſle greatly, and become a rich man.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:24001:16"/>
               <list>
                  <head>Theſe enſuing are the happie dayes, in number. 27.</head>
                  <item>IAnuary hath two, the 3. and 26.</item>
                  <item>February hath three, the 15. 19. and 26.</item>
                  <item>March hath two, the 20. and 26.</item>
                  <item>Aprill hath three, the 12. 19. and 24.</item>
                  <item>May hath three, the 7. 24. and 29.</item>
                  <item>Iune hath one, which is the 22.</item>
                  <item>Iuly hath two, the 3. and 4.</item>
                  <item>Auguſt hath three, the 2. 22. and. 28.</item>
                  <item>September hath two, the 13. and 24.</item>
                  <item>October hath one, which is the 5.</item>
                  <item>Nouember hath two, the 3. and 29.</item>
                  <item>December hath three, the 8. 16. and 24.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Theſe dayes are ſayd to be vnfortunate.</head>
                  <item>IAnuary hath two, the 5. and 25.</item>
                  <item>February hath three, the 7. 18. and 24.</item>
                  <item>March hath foure, the 6. 7 8. and 28.</item>
                  <item>Aprill hath two, the 5. and 27.</item>
                  <item>May hath three, the 5. 7. and 27,</item>
                  <item>Iune hath none.</item>
                  <item>Iuly hath two, the 5. and 8.</item>
                  <item>Auguſt hath two, the 9. and 10.</item>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:24001:16"/>
                  <item>September hath three, the 6. 8. and 26.</item>
                  <item>October hath none.</item>
                  <item>Nouember hath foure, the 4. 6. 26. and 27.</item>
                  <item>December hath ſixe, the 1, 22. 23. 25. 27. &amp; 29.</item>
               </list>
               <p>A certaine Philoſophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſayth, that one ought neuer to vndertake nor b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gin any thing of long continuance in theſe enſuing dayes, <hi>viz.</hi> The. 1. of March, the. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. of Iuly, &amp; the. 25. of Auguſt.</p>
               <p>And in the yeere are three dayes, whereon great heede muſt be taken eyther of ouer-eating or ouer-drinking: the. 6. of the Ralendes of Aprill, the. 21. of Nouember, and the. 22. of Iuly: for that on theſe dayes, one myght eaſily fall into a great languiſhing Sickneſſe, and danger of death: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe dayes ought to be ſhunned by all men, for elſe a man may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wittingly caſt himſelfe away, and cut off his life before his time: for theſe day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are called croſſe or ſtraying dayes, and therefore it is written in the Goſpell, <q>
                     <hi>Primum querite r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gnum De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; omnia Adijcicntur vobis.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
